<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Daniel G. Plaza</title>
    <link>http://danielgplaza.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Daniel G. Plaza</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; Copyright 2020 Daniel Gonzalez Plaza</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://danielgplaza.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A functional implementation Depth-First Search</title>
      <link>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2020/functional-dfs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2020/functional-dfs/</guid>
      <description>For the last few weeks I have been learning Racket. Coincidentally, Advent Of Code is back one more year. I decided to try to solve it with Racket, to force myself to learn more about the syntax and, well, use it.
In particular, Day 7 is a graph problem. Basically we want to see how many vertices can reach a particular destination.
This is straighforward. We can use breadth-first search (BFS) or depth-first search (DFS) on every vertex, and that way we&amp;rsquo;ll know how many can reach it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OOP and cars</title>
      <link>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2020/oop-and-cars/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2020/oop-and-cars/</guid>
      <description>When I first learned Object Oriented Programming (OOP) a few years ago the book I was reading had a strange obsession with cars.
Imagine you have a car, it said. A car is composed of a body, four tires, and an engine. Furthermore, you can have a Ferrari, which is a specific type of car, or you could build cars with different types of wheels. This is the way it explained the concepts of Polymorfism, Inheritance, Composition, and Instantiation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On tests, sensitivity, and specificity</title>
      <link>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2020/sensitivity-and-specificity/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2020/sensitivity-and-specificity/</guid>
      <description>Disclaimer: This page neds javascript to render LaTeX and Bokeh content.
I few days ago I was reading a Spanish newspaper and one of the headlines was how the government had acquired some tests with a sensitivity of 30% [1]. The article indicated that this was bad. But how bad? I wondered. What does it mean exactly?
In this entry I will explain the following terms:
 Sensitivity, also known as true positive rate, the recall, or probability of detection.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Receiving images from the ISS</title>
      <link>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2019/sstv/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2019/sstv/</guid>
      <description>The ISS (International Space Station) has a radio and its crew sometimes uses to communicate with amateur radio operators and also, from time to time, to send images back to Earth!
The format they use is called SSTV (Slow Scan television), in particular its format PD120. It takes around 2 minutes to receive a full image. And you can receive this images yourself by using a small handheld radio.
How to do it This is the image I was able to capture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Measurement by Paul Lockhart - A review</title>
      <link>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2019/measurement/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2019/measurement/</guid>
      <description>A few weeks ago I discovered somewhat serendipitously the book &amp;ldquo;Measurement&amp;rdquo; by Paul Lockhart. Even though I haven&amp;rsquo;t finished it yet I want to share some of my thoughts on this excellent book.
The Joy of Mathematics If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever taken a maths class (high school or undergrad level), the way it&amp;rsquo;s usually thought is &amp;ldquo;Here is this theorem, here is the proof on why it&amp;rsquo;s true. Here you have some exercises to apply this new theorem&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shuffling and permutations</title>
      <link>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2019/shuffling-and-permutations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2019/shuffling-and-permutations/</guid>
      <description>How would you shuffle a deck of cards? A couple of weeks ago I was talking to a friend about the problem of shuffling a deck of cards. His take on it was to do:
for i = 1 to n do a[i] = i for i = 1 to n-1 do swap[a[i],a[Random[i,n]] My idea was:
for i = 1 to n do a[i] = i for i = n to 1 do swap[a[i],a[random[1,i]] Both of them seemed reasonable, but were any of them correct?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mantel Clock</title>
      <link>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2019/mantel-clock/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://danielgplaza.com/posts/2019/mantel-clock/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been attending the woodworking classes at Palo Alto High School for the last couple of years. This was my last project for the 2019 Spring term.
It&amp;rsquo;s a craftsman style mantel clock (~15&amp;rsquo; tall). I used white oak and sligthly stained it at the end. I also applied a coat of wax. The clock face is made of cedar.
It was a very technical but rewarding project. All the parts had to be carefully milled and measured to make sure they fit perfectly with each other.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>